[MUSIC]
[음악]
So, the question here is can we improve
이제 관건은 딥 특징을 통해
the model using deep features.
모델을 향상시킬 수 있는지입니다
Remember we talked about deep features.
딥 특징 기억하시죠
We explored those quite a bit in this deep learning module how deep
딥러닝 모듈에서 꽤 자세히 다뤘는데
features using a technique called transfer learning can be trained on one domain,
딥 특징은 전이 학습이란 기법으로 어느 한 영역에서 학습한 특징을
then applied to images in another domain to learn
다른 영역의 이미지에 적용해서
something with even a small amount of labeled data.
적은 양의 라벨 데이터만 주어져도 학습을 가능하게 합니다
So in this case, let's just take a look at the length of our train data,
감 잡기 위해 훈련 데이터의 길이를 보면
just to get a sense of, we have, well we have 2,000 images so
이미지가 2000장인데
this is a pretty small data set.
꽤 작은 데이터 세트라고 할 수 있죠
And so, we can go ahead and see, well can we just
이제 살펴보면서 훈련 이미지 2000장과
20,000 train images using some deep features.
딥 특징만 가지고 뭘 할 수 있는지 봅니다
So this is the step you take.
순서는 이렇습니다
So we're gonna load deep_learning_model
미리 훈련된 모델인
that was pre-trained and so
deep_learning_model를
here you can use graphlab.load_model to load the model.
graphlab.load_model로 불러옵니다
And have a model that will stream on the image net data.
이미지넷 데이터를 불러옵니다
It's over here.
여깄습니다
It's called imagenet _model.
imagenet_model이라 이름짓죠
And this model stream of 1.5 million images,
모델에 150만장의 이미지와
a thousand different categories, a different data set,
천 개의 카테고리, 다양한 데이터 세트
1.5 million images, it was what we discussed, the AlexNet model.
150만개의 이미지와 AlexNet 모델입니다
It got medium easy access in 2012 ImageNet competition, so
2012년 이미지넷 대회에서 놀라운 정확도를 보였는데
I pretrained a model, and then you can use the model to create
모델을 미리 훈련시키고 이를 통해
in our image train a new column called
deep_feature라는
'deep_features'.
새로운 열을 만듭니다
And in this new column 'deep_features' what we're gonna do
이 열에 방금 불러온
is take this deep_learning_model that we just loaded.
deep_learning_model을 넣습니다
Deep_learning_model.
deep_learning_model
And I'm going to apply a function called extract_features and
extract_features를 호출할 텐데
what the extract_features does is extract those deep features.
딥 특징을 추출하는 함수죠
So does it transfer learning, taking features of learning one domain and
전이 학습, 즉 어느 한 영역에서 학습된 특징을
applies a data set in different domain.
데이터 세트의 다른 영역에 적용합니다
So this data set here is my image train data.
데이터 세트는 이미지 훈련 데이터죠
So this is the two commands that you have to do.
이게 입력해야 하는 두 명령어입니다
Pretty simple.
간단하죠
Let me decrease the font size so that it'll be a little bit more visible.
잘 보이도록 폰트 크기를 줄입니다
The two commands that you have to do to do the transfer learning.
전이 학습을 하기 위한 명령어 둘입니다
So take the image net training on the network and
이미지넷의 신경망 훈련 데이터를
apply it to this Safari 10 dataset.
CIFAR-10 데이터 세트에 적용합니다
Now computing this deep features takes a few minutes and
딥 특징 계산은 몇 분쯤 걸리는데
so I'm not going to do this right now.
지금 하지는 않을 겁니다
Instead I'm just gonna tell you that our deep mod.
대신에
If I show you the image_train data.
image_train에서
What I did was, if I just show you the head, the first few lines.
먼저 헤드, 처음 몇 줄을 보여드리죠
What you'll see is that we have an image id, we have an image, which
이미지 ID, 보고 있는 이미지,
we'll looking at, you have the label, and you have a column for deep features.
라벨, 딥 특징 열도 있습니다
So I precomputed that, and I saved it inside the s frame.
미리 계산해서 SFrame에 저장해뒀습니다
So it's already saved and precomputed.
So it's already saved and precomputed. 미리 계산 후 저장됐습니다
And it also has another column image_array that has the raw pixels that we used to
image_array란 열도 있는데
train the raw pixel model.
픽셀 모델 훈련시킬 때 썼던 겁니다
So the deep_features are already in there.
deep_features는 이미 있지만
But if you run those two commands, you'd be computing them yourself on this data
두 명령어를 실행하면 데이터 세트에서
set, or in any data set that you want.
직접 계산해볼 수 있습니다
So let's go ahead and
이제 딥 특징이
now that we have the deep features,
생겼습니다
let's train a deep model.
딥 모델을 훈련시키죠
So, Given the deep features,
딥 특징이 주어졌으니
let's train a classifier.
분류기를 훈련시킵니다
So now, we're gonna train a simple classifier using the deep features.
이제 딥 특징을 통해 간단한 분류기를 훈련시킵니다
I'm gonna call this deep_ features_model instead of the raw pixel model.
deep_features_model이라 부르죠
And the deep_features_model is also gonna be just calling logistical regression.
deep_features_model에도 로지스틱 회귀를 호출합니다
So .create and if you remember from lecture, we discussed that you can take
강의 내용을 기억하시면 이 딥 특징들을
those deep features and plug in a simple classifier at the end in this case, so
마지막에 간단한 분류기에 집어넣게 되죠
just plug in logistical regression.
이 경우 로지스틱 회귀입니다
So as input, I'm gonna give it the image_train_data.
입력은 image_train_data이 됩니다
And for features,
특징으로는
instead of using the raw pixel,
픽셀이 아닌
I'm going to use the deep_features.
deep_features를 사용합니다
And finally, I'm gonna tell it that the label, sorry, the target,
마지막으로 예측하고자 하는 대상은
the thing that I'm trying to predict here, is given by the label column.
라벨 열입니다
And there you go.
다 됐습니다
So now, we're learning a classifier and it's down here,
이제 분류기를 학습시키는데 끝났네요
using on those 2,000 images only using,
이미지 2000장과 2012년 딥러닝 대회에서 우승한
using features completed in this deep near network,
딥 신경망에서 계산된
the one in 2012 deep learning competition.
특징만을 사용했습니다
So now, let's first explore the model, just apply it for some data.
이제 모델을 탐색하고 데이터에 적용합니다
So, I'm going to, we're gonna
이제 할 건
Apply the deep features model
딥 특징 모델을 테스트 세트의
to the first few images of test set.
처음 몇 이미지에 적용하기
Just like we did with the raw pixel model, we're gonna apply it in this case.
픽셀 모델에서 했던 것처럼 적용합니다
So remember we took the image_test data and we looked at the first three images.
image_test 데이터에서 처음 세 이미지를 봅니다
So 0, 1 and 2.
0,1,2이죠
And here's what those images look like.
이런 모습들입니다
And I'm gonna type .show and
.show를 입력하면
just remind you that we have a cat, a car, and another cat.
고양이, 차, 고양이가 있었죠
And let's go ahead and just run this to see what we predict.
이제 뭐라고 예측하나 봅시다
So I'm gonna take my deep_feature_model,
deep_feature_model로
and I'm going to predict on this three images,
세 이미지를 예측합니다
so image_test of 0:3.
image_test[0:3]
And remember cat, car.
고양이, 차, 고양이인데
Cat and it says cat, automobile, cat.
고양이, 자동차, 고양이라고 하네요
So basically it got those three exactly right.
세 개 모두 맞췄습니다
Which is exciting.
훌륭하네요
So something that sucked really, really did badly using the raw pixels.
픽셀만으론 성능이 아주 나빴는데
Now using these deep features as well, on those three points it gets exactly right.
딥 특징을 함께 사용하니 다 맞췄습니다
But let's actually evaluate the deep model more formally.
딥 모델을 공식적으로 평가하죠
So, we're gonna do next is compute
deep_features_model에서
the test_data accuracy of
test_data의
the deep_features_model.
정확도를 계산합니다
And here we go.
됐지요
So how we're gonna do that?
어떻게 할까요?
We're just gonna do deep_features_model.evaluate
픽셀 모델에서 했던 것처럼
just like we did with the raw pixel model.
evaluate 함수를 호출합니다
Here we can do .evaluate.
evaluate를 붙입니다
And as input we're gonna give it the test data.
입력으로 테스트 데이터를 줍니다
So image_test.
image_test죠
And remember the raw pixel model got 46% accuracy.
And remember the raw pixel 픽셀 모델은 46% 정확도였죠
It was bad.
아주 낮았습니다
Here by using deep features we now get 78% accuracy, which is quite good.
딥 특징을 쓰니 78% 정확도가 나오네요 꽤 좋습니다
It's close to state of the art.
이게 지금으로선 최고에 가깝습니다
Even if you're learning more data it's quite good compared to the 46%.
데이터를 더 학습시켜야 하긴 하지만 46%보다는 훨씬 낫습니다
So the deep features provide you with a great tool for
딥 특징을 쓰면 데이터를 조금만 더해도
taking just a little bit small piece of data, running for the deep features and
이미지 분류 작업에서
get quite good accuracy doing image classification task here.
상당히 높은 정확도를 보여주죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]